George S. Patton Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
George S. Patton Papers 1807-1979 (bulk 1904-1945)
MSS35634
Patton, George S. (George Smith), 1885-1945
26,100 items
78 containers plus 23 oversize
40 linear feet
10 microfilm reels
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
United States Army officer. Correspondence, memoranda, diaries, journals, writings, speeches and lectures, military papers, scrapbooks, military publications, maps, photographs, and other papers relating primarily to Patton's military career as a student at the U.S. Military Academy (1904-1909), member of John J. Pershing's Punitive Expedition into Mexico (1916), aide-de-camp to Pershing and later tank commander in Europe during World War I, and commander of forces in Europe and North Africa during World War II.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Allen, Terry de la Mesa, 1888-1969--Correspondence.; Arnold, Henry Harley, 1886-1950--Correspondence.; Ayer, Charles Fanning, 1865-1956--Correspondence.; Ayer, Frederick, 1917?-1974--Correspondence.; Bradley, Omar Nelson, 1893-1981--Correspondence.; Brown, Arvin H.--Correspondence.; Clark, Mark W. (Mark Wayne), 1896-1984--Correspondence.; Clay, Lucius D. (Lucius DuBignon), 1897-1978--Correspondence.; Codman, Charles R.--Correspondence.; Crittenberger, Willis Dale, 1890-1980--Correspondence.; Devers, Jacob L. (Jacob Loucks), 1887-1979--Correspondence.; Dillingham, Walter Francis, 1875-1968--Correspondence.; Doolittle, James Harold, 1896-1993--Correspondence.; Eddy, Manton S. (Manton Sprague), 1892-1962--Correspondence.; Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969--Correspondence.; Ennis, Riley Finlay, 1897- --Correspondence.; Flint, Harry Albert, -1944--Correspondence.; Gay, Hobart R. (Hobart Raymond), 1894-1983--Correspondence.; George, Charles P., 1886-1946--Correspondence.; Gillem, Alvan Cullom, 1888-1973--Correspondence.; Grow, Robert W., 1895-1985--Correspondence.; Haislip, Wade H. (Wade Hampton), 1889-1971--Correspondence.; Handy, Thomas T. (Thomas Troy), 1892-1982--Correspondence.; Harbord, James G. (James Guthrie), 1866-1947--Correspondence.; Harmon, Ernest Nason, 1894-1979--Correspondence.; Henry, Guy Vernor, 1839-1899--Correspondence.; Hodges, Courtney H., 1887-1966--Correspondence.; Joyce, Kenyon Ashe, 1879-1960--Correspondence.; Juin, Alphonse, 1888-1967--Correspondence.; Keyes, Geoffrey, 1888-1967--Correspondence.; Lee, John Clifford Hodges, 1887-1958--Correspondence.; Lodge, Henry Cabot, Jr., 1902-1985--Correspondence.; Lucas, John Porter, 1890-1949--Correspondence.; Marshall, George C. (George Catlett), 1880-1959--Correspondence.; McNair, Lesley James, 1883-1944--Correspondence.; Merrill, Keith, 1887-1959--Correspondence.; Middleton, Troy H. (Troy Houston), 1889-1976--Correspondence.; Miles, Sherman, 1882-1966--Correspondence.; Noguès, Charles, 1876-1971--Correspondence.; Oliphant, Elmer Q. (Elmer Quillen), 1893-1975--Correspondence.; Parks, Floyd Lavinius, 1896-1959--Correspondence.; Patton, Beatrice Banning Ayer, 1886-1953--Correspondence.; Patton, George S. (George Smith), 1885-1945--Correspondence.; Patton, George S. (George Smith), 1885-1945.; Paul, Willard Stewart, 1894-1966--Correspondence.; Pershing, John J. (John Joseph), 1860-1948--Correspondence.; Pershing, John J. (John Joseph), 1860-1948.; Scott, Charles L. (Charles Lewis), 1883-1954--Correspondence.; Simpson, William H. (William Hood), 1888-1980--Correspondence.; Smith, Walter Bedell, 1895-1961--Correspondence.; Somervell, Brehon Burke, 1892-1955--Correspondence.; Spaatz, Carl, 1891-1974--Correspondence.; Stimson, Henry L. (Henry Lewis), 1867-1950--Correspondence.; Summerall, Charles Pelot, 1867-1955--Correspondence.; Surles, Alexander D. (Alexander Day), 1886-1947--Correspondence.; Truscott, Lucian King, 1895-1965--Correspondence.; Ulio, James Alexander, 1882-1958--Correspondence.; Walker, Walton Harris, 1889-1950--Correspondence.; Wallace, Frederick C.--Correspondence.; Williams, J. J. Bethurun--Correspondence.; Wood, John Shirley, 1888-1966--Correspondence.
Organizations
United States Military Academy.; United States. Army--History--Punitive Expedition into Mexico, 1916.
Subjects
Cavalry.; Denazification.; Refugees.; Sabers.; Tank warfare.; War casualties.; World War, 1914-1918--Europe--Tank warfare.; World War, 1939-1945--Africa, North.; World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns--Africa, North.; World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns--France--Normandy.; World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns--Germany.; World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns--Italy--Sicily.; World War, 1939-1945--Europe.
Titles
George S. Patton Papers: Diaries, 1910 to 1945, at the Library of Congress
Occupations
Army officers.
Provenance
The papers of George S. Patton, army officer and author, were given to the Library of Congress in 1955 by Mrs. Samuel J. Graham and in 1964 by George S. Patton IV, Mrs. James W. Totten, John Knight Waters, Jr., and George Patton Waters. Additional material was received from the Patton family, some via Martin Blumenson, and from Culbreth Sudler, Jr., from 1970 to 1986.
Transfers
Duplicate maps have been transferred to the Library's Geography and Map Division where they are identified as part of these papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of George S. Patton are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Microfilm
A microfilm edition of a portion of these papers is available from the Library's Photoduplication Service for purchase subject to the Copyright Law of the United States (Title 17, U.S.C.). A microfilm copy of one volume of Patton's diary on one reel may be requested on interlibrary loan through the Library's Loan Division. The United States Department of the Army's two reels of microfilm containing Patton's personnel file and the microfilm of the scrapbooks on seven reels are not available for interlibrary loan. To promote preservation of the originals, researchers are required to consult the microfilm edition as available.
Online Content
Diaries in the papers of George S. Patton are available on the Library of Congress Web site at http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.mss/collmss.ms000047.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1885, Nov. 11 Born, San Gabriel, Calif.
1903 1904 Attended Virginia Military Institute, Lexington, Va.
1909 Graduated, United States Military Academy, West Point, N.Y. Assigned to Fifteenth United States Cavalry, Fort Sheridan, Ill., and Fort Myer, Va.
1910 Married Beatrice Banning Ayer
1912 Member, American team, XII Olympiad, Stockholm, Sweden, finishing fifth in modern pentathlon
1912 1913 Attended French cavalry school, Saumur, France
1913 Graduated, United States Cavalry School, Fort Riley, Kans.
1913 1915 Instructor in weapons, United States Cavalry School, Fort Riley, Kans.
1915 1916 Assigned to Eighth United States Cavalry, Fort Bliss, Tex.
1916 1917 Aide-de-camp to General John J. Pershing,; Mexican Punitive Expedition
1917 Aide-de-camp to General John J. Pershing, Commander-in-Chief, American Expeditionary Forces Commanded Headquarters Troop, American Expeditionary Forces
1917 1918 Detailed as first member of American Tank Corps and attended French Tank School, Camplieu, France Organized American Tank School, Langres, France
1918 Promoted to temporary rank of lieutenant colonel
1918 1921 Commander, 304th Tank Brigade
1919 1921 Invented a coaxial gun mount
1921 1922 Commander, First Squadron, Third United States Cavalry, Fort Myer, Va.
1923 1928 United States Army General Staff, Boston, Mass., 1923-1924; Hawaii, 1924-1928
1928 1931 Served in Office of the Chief of Cavalry, United States Army
1932 Graduated, United States Army War College
1932 1935 Executive officer, Third United States Cavalry, Fort Myer, Va.
1934 Promoted to lieutenant colonel
1935 1937 G-2, United States Army General Staff, Hawaiian Department
1938 Promoted to colonel Commander, Fifth United States Cavalry, Fort Clark, Tex.
1938 1940 Commander, Third United States Cavalry, Fort Myer, Va.
1940 Promoted to brigadier general
1940 1941 Commander, Second Armored Brigade, Second Armored Division, Fort Benning, Ga.
1941 Promoted to major general
1941 1942 Commander, Second Armored Division, Fort Benning, Ga.
1942 Commander, I Armored Corps, First and Second Armored Divisions
1942 1943 Commanded Western Task Force during Allied landings and subsequent campaign in North Africa Transferred to command of United States II Corps
1943 Promoted to lieutenant general Relinquished command of II Corps to Omar Nelson Bradley Resumed command of I Armored Corps in preparation for invasion of Sicily
1943 1944 Commanded Seventh United States Army in Sicilian campaign
1944 Ordered to England to take command of Third United States Army in preparation for invasion of France
1944 1945 Commanded Third United States Army in drive across France, Germany, Czechoslovakia, and Austria
1945 Commander, Fifteenth United States Army
1945, Dec. 21 Died, Heidelberg, Germany
Scope and Content Note
The papers of George Smith Patton (1885-1945) span the years 1807-1979, with the bulk of the papers concentrated from 1904 to 1945. The collection documents Patton's military career, including his attendance at the United States Military Academy at West Point, 1904-1909; his service on the Mexican border as a member of John J. Pershing's; Mexican Punitive Expedition, 1916-1917; his service as an aide-de-camp to Pershing and later as a tank commander in World War I, 1917-1919; and his military career from 1938 to 1945. The majority of the papers chronicle Patton's World War II service and his success as one of America's most skillful combat commanders of armored troops. The papers consist of eleven series: Diaries, Chronological File, Family Papers, Correspondence, Military Papers, Military Library, Maps, Photographs, Speeches and Writings File, Miscellany, and Oversize. Most of the series relate to Patton's personal and military activities and his leadership in the development and tactical use of the tank as a combat weapon. Additional papers concerning Patton's service in World War I are in the Chester Fritz Library of the University of North Dakota located near Grand Forks, North Dakota.
The Diaries, 1910-1945, illustrate Patton's activities during the Mexican Punitive Expedition, World War I, and World War II. The volumes, particularly from 1942 to 1945, document Patton's daily activities and observations and reveal his candor about himself, personally and professionally. They include information about American ground combat operations in the campaign for North Africa, the invasion of Sicily, the liberation of France, and the final assault on Germany. Annotated volumes covering World War II often contain additional detail expanding on the original volume entries. The original diaries are dated through 24 March 1945, while annotated transcripts continue to 3 December 1945. The Library did not receive the latter portion of the original diaries. Additional topics include Patton's honeymoon trip to Europe in 1910 and his fox hunting activities, 1932-1935.
The Chronological File, 1901-1977, provides an overview of Patton's life, serving as a combination diary-scrapbook consisting mainly of diary entries, correspondence, memoranda, and reports. Approximately one half of the series is in transcript form. The originals of these transcripts are located in other series. This series also contains original items, primarily correspondence, that do not appear in any other series.
The Family Papers, 1857-1979, consist mainly of Patton's letters to his wife, Beatrice Banning Ayer Patton, and his father, George S. Patton (1856-1927). Early letters chronicle Patton's struggle as a student at West Point. His letters to his wife are detailed and, like the diaries, contain frank assessments of commanders, subordinates, and military operations. Patton shared not only his achievements with his wife but also some of the negative incidents that affected his career, such as the reaction in November 1943 when the press reported that he had slapped two soldiers suffering battle fatigue in Sicily and his remarks in a speech in Knutsford, England, in April 1944 omitting inclusions of Russia as one of the countries likely to rule the postwar world with the United States and Great Britain. Both incidents threatened his career and almost resulted in his removal from the war. Also in the Family Papers are correspondence of Beatrice Patton and an autobiographical account of Patton's memories of his father. There is a significant amount of printed matter of George H. Smith, Patton's step-grandfather, concerning the Civil War battle of New Market, Virginia.
Papers in the Correspondence series, 1903-1945, include incoming and outgoing correspondence between Patton and his staff, commanders, government officials, friends, and the general public. Because many of Patton's friends and colleagues were in the military, there is a significant amount of material in the chronological correspondence that relates to military matters. The official correspondence documents the planning of various combat operations, particularly for the Allied invasion of Sicily and D-Day planning for France and reflects Patton's varied duties as a commander. The topical correspondence includes fan mail, inquiries on casualties, furloughs and discharges, the slapping incidents in Sicily, and Christmas and get-well letters sent to Patton after his automobile accident in December 1945.
The Military Papers, 1903-1976, consist of administrative files, Patton's personnel file, and a subject file. The bulk of the series illustrates Patton's duties while a combat commander from 1942 to 1945. The files include orders, citations, memoranda, speeches, training instructions, policy and procedural material, and reports concerning units Patton commanded. Speeches made by Patton to his troops during World War II were originally filed in the Military Papers, and this order has been retained. Duplicates of some of these speeches are filed in the Speeches and Writings File. Documents relating to Patton's personnel file include both personal and official papers. The official papers are included in a microfilm copy of Patton's file in the records of the Department of the Army. Prominent topics featured in the subject file are the cavalry, casualty information, denazification of Germany, displaced persons, and tanks. Much of the material relating to tanks concerns the development of that vehicle and the tactics of armored warfare. The series also contains material relating to Patton's death and funeral.
The Military Library series, 1907-1947, includes class publications from West Point, intelligence and campaign reports, and other material relating to military tactics. The majority of the series consists of campaign reports pertaining to France and Germany.
Items in the Maps series, 1906-1945, reflect Patton's interest in cartography. Most of the items are situation maps of the European theater and commemorative maps of the United States Third Army's operations in Europe. A map of Western Europe, marked by Patton in March 1944 prior to the development of campaign plans, illustrates with remarkable accuracy the projected route that the Third Army would take in its advance across France and Germany.
The Photographs series, 1864-1958, consist primarily of items relating to Patton's military career, although there are a few family photographs in the "Miscellaneous" folders. Locations featured in the World War II pictures include North Africa, Sicily, England, France, and Germany. Also well represented are Patton's years at the military academy at West Point, his tenure at Fort Meade, Maryland, and his service with the Mexican Punitive Expedition. World War II "Miscellaneous" folders include photographs, some autographed, of Patton's superiors and fellow officers.
Papers in the Speeches and Writings File, 1900-1947, consist chiefly of articles, speeches, reports, lectures, book reviews, memoranda, poetry, and memoirs. A few writings of others interfiled in this series with Patton's texts are listed in a partial index compiled by Patton. Prominent topics featured in Patton's writings include the saber, the cavalry, mechanization, tanks, and tank tactics. Patton's writings illustrate his early interest in armored warfare and indicate his belief in the tank as an important combat weapon long before its success in World War II. A 1937 paper entitled "Surprise" includes Patton's prediction of an attack by Japan on Pearl Harbor.
The Miscellany series, 1911-1966, includes biographical information, certificates and citations, reports, and printed matter relating chiefly to Patton's participation in the pentathlon in the 1912 Olympics in Stockholm, his interests in fencing and swordsmanship, and his attendance at the Mounted Service School, Fort Riley, Kansas. Also documented in the series are the various medals and honors awarded Patton during his lifetime and posthumously. The Oversize series, 1807-1951, consists principally of maps, overlays, photograph albums, and scrapbooks of newspaper clippings, correspondence, photographs, and other printed matter.
Prominent among Patton's correspondents are Harold Alexander (Earl Alexander of Tunis),; Terry de la Mesa Allen,; Henry Harley Arnold,; Charles Fanning Ayer,; Frederick Ayer,; Omar Nelson Bradley,; Arvin H. Brown,; Mark W. Clark,; Lucius D. Clay,; Charles R. Codman,; Willis Dale Crittenberger,; Jacob L. Devers,; Walter Francis Dillingham,; James Harold Doolittle,; Manton S. Eddy,; Dwight D. Eisenhower,; Riley Finlay Ennis,; Harry Albert Flint,; Hobart R. Gay,; Charles P. George,; Alvan Cullom Gillem, Jr.,; Robert W. Grow,; Wade H. Haislip,; Thomas T. Handy,; James G. Harbord,; Ernest Nason Harmon,; Guy Vernor Henry,; Courtney H. Hodges,; Kenyon Ashe Joyce,; Alphonse Juin,; Geoffrey Keyes,; John Clifford Hodges Lee,; Henry Cabot Lodge,; John Porter Lucas,; Lesley James McNair,; George C. Marshall,; Keith Merrill,; Troy H. Middleton,; Sherman Miles,; Charles (August Paul) Noguès,; Elmer Q. Oliphant,; Floyd Lavinius Parks,; Willard Stewart Paul,; John J. Pershing,; Charles L. Scott,; William H. Simpson,; Walter Bedell Smith,; Brehon Burke Somervell,; Carl Spaatz,; Henry Lewis Stimson,; Charles Pelot Summerall,; Alexander D. Surles,; Lucian King Truscott,; James Alexander Ulio,; Walton Harris Walker,; Frederick C. Wallace,; J. J. Bethurun Williams, and John Shirley Wood.
Throughout his papers, Patton used nicknames, abbreviations, and code words to denote certain persons and operations. The following names and words are found primarily in his World War II diaries and correspondence and the chronological file for those years:
"Ike," "d," "D," "Destiny"--Dwight D. Eisenhower
"Brad," "tent maker"--Omar Nelson Bradley
"P"--John Shirley Wood
"Hap"--Henry Harley Arnold
"Critt"--Willis Dale Crittenberger
"Jake"--Jacob L. Devers
"Tody"--Charles P. George
"Van"--Alvan Cullom Gillem, Jr.
"Beadle"--Walter Bedell Smith
"Tooey"--Carl Spaatz
"Day"--Alexander D. Surles
"Paddy"--Harry Albert Flint
"Husky"--Allied invasion of Sicily, 10 July 1943
"Bigot"--D-Day planning, 1944
Organization of the Papers
The collection is arranged in twelve series:
Diaries, 1910-1945
Chronological File, 1901-1977
Family Papers, 1857-1979
Correspondence, 1903-1945
Military Papers, 1903-1976
Military Library, 1907-1947
Maps, 1906-1945
Photographs, 1864-1958
Speeches and Writings File, 1900-1947
Miscellany, 1911-1966
Manuscript Material Removed from Scrapbooks After Microfilming, 1807-1950
Oversize, 1807-1951
Container List
- Diaries, 1910-1945 (Box 1-3)
  Holograph and typewritten diaries, bound and unbound.
  Arranged in two groups, original and annotated transcripts, and therein chronologically.
  The diary for Sept. 24-Mar. 5, 1943, is available on microfilm. Shelf no. 20,613.
  - Original (Box 1)
    - 1910
    - 1914, 1916, and 1917
    - 1918-1919
    - 1942, Aug. 5-17
    - 1942, Sept. 24-1943, Mar. 5, Diary available on microfilm. Shelf no. 20,613
    - 1943, Mar. 5-May 21
    - 1943, May 21-July 2
    - 1943, July-Nov. 12
    - 1943, Nov. 13-1944, May 31
    - 1944, May 31-Oct. 2
    - 1944, Oct. 3-1945, Feb. 5
    - 1945, Feb. 5-Mar. 24
  - Annotated transcripts (Box 2)
    - 1916
    - 1916
    - 1917, May-July
    - 1917, Aug.-Dec.
    - 1918, Jan.-Mar.
    - 1918, Apr.-June
    - 1918, July-Dec.
    - 1919
    - 1932-1933
    - 1933-1934
    - 1934-1935 (1 of 2)
    - 1934-1935 (2 of 2)
    - 1942, Aug.-1943, Jan. 25
    - 1943, Jan. 26-Apr. 8
    - 1943, Apr. 8-July 1
    - 1943-1945, (13 folders) (Box 3)
      - 1943, July 1-23
      - 1943, July 24-Aug. 26
      - 1943, Aug. 26-1944, Feb. 8 (1 of 2)
      - 1943, Aug. 26-1944, Feb. 8 (2 of 2)
      - 1944, Feb. 10-July 31 (1 of 2)
      - 1944, Feb. 10-July 31 (2 of 2)
      - 1944, Aug. 1-Nov. 29 (1 of 2)
      - 1944, Aug. 1-Nov. 29 (2 of 2)
      - 1944, Nov. 30-1945, Mar. 22 (1 of 2)
      - 1944, Nov. 30-1945, Mar. 22 (2 of 2)
      - 1945, Mar. 22-Sept. 26 (1 of 2)
      - 1945, Mar. 22-Sept. 26 (2 of 2)
      - 1945, Sept. 27-Dec. 3
- Chronological File, 1901-1977 (Box 4-14)
  A collection of diary entries, correspondence, school papers, memoranda, reports, photographs, articles, speeches, lectures, maps, notebooks, orders, citations, newspaper clippings, printed matter, and other material.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1901-1906, (16 folders) (Box 4)
  - 1907-1913, (17 folders) (Box 5)
  - 1914-1916, (12 folders) (Box 6)
  - 1917
    - 1917, Jan.-Aug., (5 folders)
    - 1917, Sept.-Dec., (6 folders) (Box 7)
  - 1918
    - 1918, Jan.-Mar., (7 folders)
    - 1918, Apr.-Sept. See also Oversize, (17 folders) (Box 8)
    - 1918, Oct.-Dec. See also Oversize, (7 folders) (Box 9)
  - 1919-1920 See also Oversize, (12 folders)
  - 1922-1942 See also Oversize, (12 folders) (Box 10)
  - 1943
    - 1943, Jan.-Apr., (5 folders)
    - 1943, May-Dec., (13 folders) (Box 11)
  - 1944
    - 1944, Jan.-Apr., (4 folders)
    - 1944, May-Dec. See also Oversize, (17 folders) (Box 12)
  - 1945
    - 1945, Jan., (2 folders)
    - 1945, Feb.-Oct., (17 folders) (Box 13)
    - 1945, Nov.
      - 1-11, (2 folders)
      - 12-29, (2 folders) (Box 14)
    - 1945, Dec. See also Oversize, (2 folders)
  - 1946-1963, 1970-1971, 1977, undated, (9 folders)
- Family Papers, 1857-1979 (Box 14-24)
  Correspondence between Patton and family members with attachments and enclosures, genealogical material, printed matter, and miscellaneous papers relating to the family.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material and therein by name of family member.
  - Correspondence (Box 14)
    - Ayer, Charles Fanning (brother-in-law), 1917, 1943-1945
    - Ayer, Ellen Barrows Banning (mother-in-law) and Frederick (father-in-law), 1908-1918, (3 folders)
    - Ayer, Frederick, (bother-in-law), 1930, 1942-1945, (2 folders)
    - Patton, Anne ("Nita") (sister), 1909, 1918-1919, 1931, 1941-1945
    - Patton, Beatrice Banning Ayer (wife)
      - Original
        - 1903-1907, (2 folders)
        - 1908-1915, (15 folders) (Box 15)
        - 1916
          - 1916, Jan.-Aug., (6 folders)
          - 1916, Sept.-Dec., (4 folders) (Box 16)
        - 1917-1919, (20 folders)
        - 1922-1943, (21 folders) (Box 17)
        - 1944, (14 folders) (Box 18)
        - 1945
          - 1945, Jan.-Feb., (2 folders)
          - 1945, Mar.-Dec., (8 folders) (Box 19)
      - Annotated typescripts
        - Set A, 1942-1944, (10 folders)
        - Set B, 1942-1943, (4 folders) (Box 20)
    - Patton, George S. (1856-1927) (father)
      - 1903-1917, (14 folders)
      - 1918-1920, 1926-1927, (2 folders) (Box 21)